Guide to the Steve Roden Collection, 2015 RL.11091
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Steve Roden collection
2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roden, Steve
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11091
2.0 Linear Feet 1 flat box; 11 prints; 2 USB keys
Steve Roden is an American sound and visual artist, and was the 2014 Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Visiting Artist in Residency at the Rubenstein Library. His collection contains prints, video, and sound files created as a result of his residency.
Biographical / Historical
Steve Roden is an American sound and visual artist, who pioneered the lowercase style of music; where quiet, usually unheard, sounds are amplified to form complex and rich soundscapes. Roden was the Rubenstein Library's 2014 Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Visiting Artist.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records. Original media has not been removed from the collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Steve Roden Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Collection Overview
Collection contains artwork created by Steve Roden as a result of his residency at the Rubenstein Library as the 2014 Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Visiting Artist. His collection consists of a box containing 11 prints and 2 thumb drives. One thumb drive contains video files, and the other contains audio files. Roden's Visual Works on Paper are accompanied by his notes explaining his thought process and questions as he worked with Rubenstein materials during his residency. His artwork was inspired by medieval manuscripts, the Irene Peslikis Papers, Julian Abele and his role as an architect for Duke University, and other unspecified collections held in the Rubenstein Library. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University).
Collages (visual works); Artists -- United States; Roden, Steve; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Abele, Julian, 1881-1950; Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library; Peslikis, Irene
- Video, 2015; 2.0 Gigabytes 1 thumb drive; Disk image derived from USB key. Image contains six video files in MOV format, approximately 2.0 gigabytes.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Although original USB key has not been removed from the collection, the electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
  Scope and Contents
  Roden's inventory accompanies the USB key with the following note: "all of these works were created in the small house i lived in while during the residency."
  - redwhite, 2015
  - doublerainbow, 2015
  - windowstriangles, 2015
  - coloredwindows, 2015
  - clips, 2015
  - falling, 2015
- Audio, 2015; 1.92 Gigabytes; Disk image derived from USB key. Disk image contains 8 audio files in WAV format, approximately 1.9 gigabytes.
  - electric robots, 2015
  - bubbles, 2015
  - ground control, 2015
  - rythmic [sic] slow quiet, 2015
  - slow haunt, 2015
  - voices, 2015
  - lost contact, 2015
- Visual Works on Paper, 2015; 11 items 1 box of artwork 11 prints, 1 inventory with notes by Roden 12.5 x 18.5 inches
  Prints held in a box created by Roden. Box is labeled "Steve Roden Archive Works for Duke." The prints are accompanied by Roden's own inventory and notes, titled "an archive for an archive from an archive," which include titles, dimensions, and details about the archive's contents as well as his thoughts and questions developed during his visiting artist residency at Rubenstein.
  - a different kind of tension (spools), 2015 (Box 1)
    Crayons, pencil, sumi ink.
    Roden's notes: "created from notes while looking at a sewing case."
  - approaching an archive, L, 2015 (Box 1)
    Roden's notes on "approaching an archive LCR": "three drawings based on some of my own questions about approaching an archive and its contents, made up of 3 works of paper that should be exhibited as a triptych. some aspects of the composition was related to notes of the form of texts in the biblia polyglotta from 1522."
  - approaching an archive, C, 2015 (Box 1)
    Crayons, pencil, sumi ink
  - approaching an archive, R, 2015 (Box 1)
  - variation 1, 2015 (Box 1)
    Collage, crayons, pencil, sumi ink.
    Roden's notes: "the four works on paper entitled 'variation' came from a manuscript titled notata, which seemed to lean towards alchemy or mystical ideas. again from my notes - incomplete and as such, all of these works converse with what i engaged with, without attempting to replicate, but to use as 'seeds'."
  - variation 2, 2015 (Box 1)
  - variation 3, 2015 (Box 1)
  - variation 4, 2015 (Box 1)
    Cardboard, collage, crayons, pencil, sumi ink
  - when architecture is like comic books, 2015 (Box 1)
    Roden's notes: "a work on paper that came out of two incidents, one was learning about the architect julian able [sic], an african american, who designed some of duke's buildings, that as an african american, was not allowed to go inside of the buildings... while not related to duke's archive, that history reminded me of the comic book artist matt baker, who in the 1940's was only aloud [sic] to draw white super-heroes, and when drawing african americans, they were usually 'bad guys' or stereotypical images of african natives (with bones in their nose and big lips) in books like tarzan or jungle tales, etc. when i learned of julian able [sic] and his inability to spend time in the spaces he designed, really stuck with me during my time at duke... and hopefully someone will pick up the thread of baker's work as well... he was a fantastic artist."
  - clothed 2, 2015 (Box 1)
    Collage parts from a 1972 magazine.
    Roden's notes: "the two collages i made were in response to the irene peslikis papers. i spent a fair amount of time with her own artworks, as well as some of the other contents of that archive. before i was finished going through everything in her archive, i noticed on the back of a drawing or a document, that she had made a small collage, most likely from a playboy magazine of a nude woman.
    like so many of the things in her archive, i felt outside of certain materials, but in this case i felt very much connected to her visual aesthetic. (obviously the content was another thing.) so there were a lot of inner conversations related to the material and how to engage with the material conscientiously... but on the other hand there is a hope that something will open up or cause trouble... and that collage certainly offered me a lot of food for thought... i have been working with small collages from 1960's magazines over the past few years, and peslikis' collages were not so distant from my own, although i wasn't pulling images from playboy. nonetheless, discovering a collage on the back side of a document also left me with a lot to think about. in the end i wanted to engage with her work because i knew there would be complications - emotionally, conceptually, socially, etc. part of me wanted to make collaged [sic] with my mother, but on the other hand since i had been working with them no for so long, i simply plowed forward. in the end, i made two large collages from a playboy magazine from the year i was born, and made collages from all kinds of images, but none of unclothed women... the hope is that my use of images from playboy will cause some problems, and overall my interest outside of the things i'm making, but to somehow have to deal with new situations simply because i was thrust into various different worlds."
  - clothed 1, 2015 (Box 1)
    Collage parts from a 1972 magazine